In March 1970, an election was held in
the small town of Bridgewater in
Somerset.
>> This is your opportunity to meet Tom
King, your Conservative candidate in
town. It was a by-election held
following the death of the town's
[music] MP, Gerald Wills. This election
would be different. See, the year
before, the government had passed the
Representation of the People Act 1969.
[music]
This lowered the minimum voting age in
the UK from 21 to 18. I think that
in 1970, probably makes some sense. I
think personally, I might have
opted for 19 or 20, but
I think 18 is
if this is the decision, I think I'm
perfectly happy with it.
>> It was a far less controversial move
than you might think. Some veterans
under the age of 21 had briefly been
granted the right to vote in the wake of
the First World War. The 1960s had also
seen a wave of youth protest and
political movements which made ignoring
the voices of 18- to 21-year-olds more
and more difficult to justify. The
change was part of a global trend. The
following year, Canada also extended the
vote to 18, 19, and 20-year-olds. The
year after that, the United States and
the Netherlands [music] did the same.
Today, it would be easier to list the
countries in which the voting age isn't
18 than those in which it is. I won't.
That would be a really boring video.
When the Labour Party under Keir Starmer
was elected in 2024, one of the pledges
contained in their manifesto was to go
one step further and reduce the voting
age once again to 60. I'm here in
Hackney, in London, to speak with the
government minister responsible for
these changes. We're also going to speak
with a bunch of students who have been
enfranchised by the move to see what
they think. Is granting 16-year-olds and
17-year-olds the right to vote a step
too far, or does it have the potential
to inject new energy into our politics
at a time when democracy across the
world is under threat?
So, I'm Sam Dixon. I'm a member of
Parliament, and I'm the Minister for
Democracy.
>> This is Samantha Dixon, who currently
holds the government brief of the
Minister for Democracy, alongside
several other roles within the Ministry
for Housing, Communities, and Local
Government. I've been doing the job
since September, and it involves
drafting legislation, which is a new law
that we're hoping to introduce very soon
about a range of different issues. Last
week, Samantha's boss, Steve Reed, stood
up in Parliament to introduce the
Representation of the People Bill 2026.
I beg to move that the bill be now read.
The bill isn't only about votes at 16.
It seeks to make a number of changes to
how elections work here in Britain.
[music] None of them are small. There
are provisions for automatic voter
registration, for making it easier to
vote by expanding the range of documents
which can be used as voter ID, and also
for tightening up rules on political
donations. In fact, one of the key
themes is about trying to shore up trust
in politics, which made it an
interesting week to be filming this
piece. Lord Mandelson is semi-undressed.
The woman he's speaking to, unknown. A
year ago, it would have been
unthinkable. Peter Mandelson, the Prime
Minister's man in America, not just
stepping down from that role, but from
the Labour [music] Party itself. Keir
Starmer is fighting for his political
life amid mounting fury over his
decision to appoint Peter Mandelson as
the UK's ambassador to the United
States. I regret appointing him.
If I knew then what I know now, he would
never been anywhere near government.
But, we'll come back to that, because I
think it's bringing the voting age down
to 16, which is the most interesting
part of these proposals. The main ones
are actually introducing votes at 16 and
17. So, it's an important piece of piece
of legislation, and I'm very pleased to
be able to be taking it to Parliament in
due course. The concept of letting 16-
and 17-year-olds vote is far from new.
Younger people need like their voice to
be heard, sometimes, cuz they're not
like understanding what we need. This is
a news package from way back in 2004,
when the Labour government under Tony
Blair considered adopting the very same
policy. Many of these young people
really do care passionately about
single-issue campaigns such as
anti-racism and anti-bullying
represented by these rubber wristbands,
but mainstream politics, perhaps
unsurprisingly, continues to pass them
by. I can only assume kids are still
wearing charity wristbands.
They just They just love that Lance
Armstrong arm guy. Blair eventually
decided against the idea after the
Electoral Commission, which oversees
Britain's elections, advised against it.
At least for the time being. The Labour
Party, however, never quite let go of
the idea. And buoyed by a widely
supported campaign from young people's
charities and organizations and civil
society, have long suggested that they
would implement it should they find
themselves back in power. Well, it's
time to do something else which is long
overdue
>> [music]
>> in our country. And the next Labour
government will do it by May 2016. And
that's to give the vote to 16- and
17-year-olds. So, you have a voice in
our democracy. [applause]
Several other major political parties
also support the move. The Liberal
Democrats, the Green Party, the Scottish
National Party, and Plaid Cymru have all
adopted a reduction in the voting age as
an official policy. At this point, it
would be easier to list the parties
which don't support it than those which
do. [music] It's effectively the Tories
Reform and the DUP.
All of whom actually think the voting
age should be 65. Yet another reason for
votes at 16. I didn't need convincing,
but you've given me another reason. Very
good.
>> I think that the voice of 16- [music]
and 17-year-olds is really important in
our democracy. I think it's a group of
young people who have a really strong
view about how our country should go
forward.
It's important that they have their say
on what happens in the [clears throat]
future. There are many things that
affect people's lives, and 16- and
17-year-olds have many pressures, many
opportunities. So, for example, they
might be thinking about their work life
ahead of them. They may be thinking
about where they're going to live and
how they're going to live. Those are
fundamental decisions that politicians
make decisions about,
but they're doing it without those young
people having their say. And I think
they really need to feel that they are
listened to. Here in the UK,
16-year-olds can join [music] the armed
forces, they can pay taxes, they can buy
liquor chocolates and party poppers. 16
is also the age of consent. There are
plenty of ways in which the government
already treats 16-year-olds like [music]
adults. And campaigners thus argue that
excluding them from being able to vote
is unjust. There's also a broader goal
here, however, in trying to infuse not
only young people, but kind of everyone
about democracy at a time when more and
more people seem to be a little bit
skeptical [music] about the system. We
also find that younger people 16, 17
year olds,
if they're allowed to vote,
>> [clears throat]
>> then they carry on voting. And so, it it
starts a lifetime of participation. And
I think
that's all to the good.
>> [music]
>> It's really healthy for our democracy
that people take part, that turnout is
up, and people feel engaged in it.
Democratic participation in the UK is
currently at desperately low levels. The
last general election saw the second
lowest voter turnout rate since
universal suffrage was granted to over
21-year-olds in 1928. It's taken us less
than 100 years to go from clamoring for
the vote to seemingly getting pretty
cold on the whole idea. You're joking.
Not another one? This is not a small
problem. The legitimacy of democratic
institutions kind of relies on people
actually participating in them. The hope
is that allowing young people to start
voting earlier might get them excited
about democracy and help to reverse this
decades-long downward trend.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So, you think you would vote now at the
end of the day?
Or you're still a bit like
I think I would. I still would cuz
obviously it is a good opportunity to
have and I wouldn't pass it up, but
I would still be a little bit more
skeptical when it comes to voting. Yeah,
definitely. I think young people bring
new ideas forward which are really
needed in politics. Speaking with the
young people in Hackney, it was clear
that not only did they think they should
have the right to vote on principle, but
that most of them would make plans to
actually go out and do so if given the
opportunity. Whether that's true of all
16 and 17-year-olds, however, is a bit
more up for debate. See, in much of UK,
the voting age already is 16, or kind
of. 16 and 17-year-olds can vote in
elections for both the Scottish
Parliament and the Welsh Senate. The
impact there has been mixed. Scotland
first lowered its voting age as a
one-off as part of its independence
referendum back in 2014. A study carried
out by the Electoral Commission shortly
after found that 75% of eligible young
people voted. Slightly lower than the
overall turnout at 84.6%,
but much higher than the 59.7% turnout
at the last general election. Those
young people have also continued to vote
in elections since. A 2021 study found
a, quote, "significant follow-through
effect in voter turnout among young
people who experienced their first
election and were enfranchised at ages
16 or 17." In Wales, the results of the
experiment has been much less decisive.
Most 16- in Wales have only been able to
vote once since they were given the
ability in 2020. Most didn't. Fewer than
45% registered to vote in the 2021
Senate elections. That being said, this
was also a COVID election, meaning that
any work aimed at engaging young people
in the process was made much harder.
Either way, Scotland and Wales reducing
their voting age for their national
elections has clearly laid the framework
for doing so for UK-wide contests, too.
My constituency is in Chester. It's on
the border with Wales. Young people in
Wales already have the vote at 16. They
have it in Scotland, as well. I actually
think that everybody in the United
Kingdom, in Northern Ireland, England,
Scotland, and Wales deserves to have the
vote at 16. It's about consistency, and
it's about fairness, and actually, it's
about increasing participation.
Of course, lowering the voting age
wouldn't only be a matter of principle.
I don't think it's particularly
controversial to suggest that over the
past couple of decades, young people
have got a pretty raw deal out of
politics. Since I went to union 2012,
just bear that figure in mind about my
debt, 37 and a half grand. Since I went
to union 2012, the amount of interest, I
did the sums before I got here, that I
have accrued is £32,000.
So, was it mis-sold to me when I was
told it was going to cost me 9 grand a
year? Yeah, I'd say so.
>> Over the last month or so, there's been
a big debate here in the UK about the
fairness or otherwise of the student
loan system. Regardless of who's right
in that conversation, one has to
conclude that one of the reasons it's
been so easy for the government to load
the burden of university onto individual
students is that the vast majority of
people who go to university do so
without ever having had had the
opportunity to vote. Contrast that with
older voters, whose ability to defend
their interests at the ballot box
ensures that the state pension [music]
continues to rise at least in line with
inflation, if not more, every single
year. Do you feel like politicians
listen to you at the moment and the sort
of issues young people care about? I
don't think it's one of the main issues
that they focus on, and I think one
thing, if it becomes 16, 17-year-olds
can vote, I think they need to like
integrate into their campaigns focusing
on them.
>> if the vote was open to us, I feel like
they would feel like they kind of have
to, and at the end of the day, having
more people to vote on, having a much
larger audience, they would feel the
need to kind of open the floor to them,
as well. Do you think we will see
politicians and political parties having
to shape [music] and policy around young
people a little bit more and and appeal
to them. Yes.
As politicians, we listen to the
electorate. If that electorate is going
to change and become younger, then we're
going to have to listen to that section
of the electorate [music] in a way that
we haven't done before. And I think
that's really good because these young
people, the decision as I said before,
the decisions that we take as
politicians affects what happens to them
and they want to say. And I think
they may have some trepidation about how
they have that say, but actually I think
when they realize that the influence and
the power that they may have, I think
that's really important.
>> [music]
>> Of course, the idea that teenagers might
gain the ability to influence policy
isn't super exciting for everyone. When
we asked them whether they think it's a
good idea to lower the voting age,
almost half said no and only 18% told us
they'd [music] definitely vote.
>> This is Louis Denison from ITV News, who
you might also catch wandering around
the background of some of our footage.
He's reporting on a poll that ITV
commissioned last summer into what young
people themselves thought about these
proposals. Nearly half said it was a bad
idea. That's right. 16- and 17-year-olds
themselves are actually pretty split on
whether they want to be able to vote in
most elections. Now, I will say that
this was a somewhat odd polling question
in which don't know apparently wasn't
given as an option. Moreover, when
Denison says that only 18% of
respondents said they would definitely
vote, the poll actually asked them to
respond on a sliding scale between 0 and
10. Only 18% answered 10, but 55% said
they were more likely to vote than not.
Nevertheless, it's clearly the case that
many people are vehemently opposed to
giving young people the vote.
>> The fact is, like you're not going to
get a 16-year-old that is going to have
the life experience of knowing what that
important vote is going to mean to them
down the line.
>> I just don't think that 16-year-olds
have a really good uh
concept of how the everything works.
>> Paul says, "Michelle, be absolutely
straight about things. Many 16-year-olds
don't have a seem to know what gender
they are, never mind who to vote for."
Some people hearing about this
announcement [music] uh who will be
thinking oh goodness, like young people
having this kind of ability
>> [music]
>> is terrifying, right? 16, 17-year-olds
not mature enough, don't know enough
about everything. And you know, I
probably did some quite silly things
when I was 16, 17. Uh
do you think they have a point at all?
I think I've said before that wisdom
isn't the preserve of any particular age
group. I think there are some very wise
16 and 17-year-olds, and there are some
very unwise
older people. I don't think it's
something that you can generalize about.
I think there are thoughtful and um
careful people in every generation, in
every age group. It That isn't a reason
to to say that people can't can't vote
responsibly, and they should They should
have that opportunity. [music] They
should be in those polling booths
casting their votes. Going back through
the archive of news stories about this
topic from over the past couple of
decades, [music]
it's interesting how many of the
arguments for lowering the voting age
have actually become weaker. Like most
adult stuff you can do, you can smoke,
you can uh um have sex. You can do loads
of stuff when you're 16, so why can't
you vote? When the prospect of lowering
the voting age was first floated in the
mid-2000s, 16-year-olds could buy
cigarettes. They could buy lottery
tickets. They could get married with the
permission of their parents.
17-year-olds could fight on the front
lines in war-zones. While 16- and
17-year-olds can still get married in
Scotland and Northern Ireland, the age
of majority for all of the [music] rest
of those activities has since been
raised to 18. You can no longer leave
education at 16. You can't use sunbeds
or get Botox. The online safety act uses
18 as the age at which people can access
online pornography and other content the
act considers harmful. 16-year-olds
can't buy a beer without a meal, but
even if they can work and pay income
tax, the reality is that most don't. In
the weeks preceding my chat with
Samantha, there'd been discussion of
whether the government might follow in
Australia's footsteps and introduce a
social media ban for under 16s. The
government has also consulted on making
16 the legal age at which you can buy an
energy drink. The far bigger issue
hanging over my conversation with
Samantha, however, was about trust in
politics. The Representation of the
People Bill isn't just about granting
16- and 17-year-olds the right to vote.
It also contains a bunch of other
provisions. The government's policy
paper outlining its plans is actually
titled Restoring Trust in Our Democracy.
The bill will introduce automated voter
registration, that will expand the kinds
of documents which can be used for voter
ID, and it will reform the way in which
donations to political candidates and
parties work. During the week in which
we were speaking, however, trust in
politics was taking a battering on
another front. The so-called Epstein
files released by the United States
Department of Justice had placed Keir
Starmer under scrutiny for having
appointed a known friend of Epstein's,
Peter [music] Mandelson, as the UK's
ambassador to the United States. This
wasn't the first time that the current
government had come under scrutiny for
decisions which were seen to undermine
trust in politics, either. It seemed
important to ask Samantha whether,
alongside whatever policy fixes might be
put in place to try and restore [music]
trust in politics, some of the onus
might be on individual politicians and
political parties [music]
to make better choices whilst in office.
This is obviously quite a
uh
an interesting week [music] in politics,
and given that one of the key themes in
a lot of the announcements around this
policy are about trust in politics. That
is a conversation that a lot of people
are talking about at the moment. [music]
Since the last general election
we've had Keir Starmer um give Peter
Mandelson the US ambassadorship. We've
had all kinds of scandals around um
ministers accepting freebies.
>> [music]
>> Um
two of the people that uh initially
designed this policy had to resign due
to housing-based scandals. There'll be
some people who'll be watching this and
be thinking, "Yes, trust in politics is
so important and yes, there are policy
ways that we can fix some of that." But
who also might be saying that if the
government was really serious about
trust in politics, they would have acted
very differently over the last 18 months
or so. We need to make sure that our
politics is really robust and secure.
People can't interfere with it. We need
to make sure that there is integrity in
the process and that's what this bill is
aiming to do. The feeling that people
have that there are donations coming in
from other sources that aren't [music]
clear
give gives a wider sense of mistrust and
I think that people need to act with
integrity [music] within politics and
actually this bill will take that
forward. I think just to push a little
bit more, I would think a lot of people
at the moment would be thinking like,
"Yes, we can do stuff about donations
and all of that kind of stuff." But
there is also always that thing of
individual politicians needing to make
choices that are outstanding and stand
up to scrutiny and and that doesn't feel
to a lot of people like that has been
happening. Well, the the accountability
that's needed in politics will be
enhanced by this bill because there will
be measures [music] that come in that
affect every candidate, every elected
representative in terms of our political
life and the donations, the income that
we receive. So, I hope that this bill
will take forward that sense of the
integrity of the process and that
actually the people who are standing and
doing the right thing
and leading
a better example towards a better, safer
democracy.
What unites all of the various
provisions of the Representation of the
People Bill
>> [music]
>> is the idea that something needs to
change with regard to the way we do
democracy here in the UK. And in 2026,
that is not a controversial point of
view. An Ipsos poll carried out at the
end of 2025 found satisfaction with
democracy to be at dangerously low
levels. Just 26% of Brits reported they
were actively satisfied [music] with
democracy, with 49% saying they were
dissatisfied. Similar sentiment was
found in Spain, Italy, the US, France,
and Croatia. Lowering the voting age
surely isn't a silver bullet. We know
that most people's concerns about
democracy are much bigger than the
voting age. Nevertheless, the
government's hope is that taking a more
proactive approach to introducing young
people to democracy while still at
school can get people excited about
being citizens and using the power that
they have to shape the future of the
country. Looking back at the decision to
lower the voting age to 18 back in 1969,
it's exactly how natural that all seems
now. I think you would struggle to find
anyone who agrees with the idea that we
should take away the vote from 18, 19,
and 20-year-olds. If this bill goes
through, which there's every reason to
think that it will, it's interesting to
consider whether we might see this move
through the same lens in another 57
years' time. What is clear is that the
generation which benefited most from
that earlier decision to lower the
voting age have ended up wielding
significant power in our society. The
cohort which came to be known as the
baby boomers both experienced and shaped
a historically unprecedented era of
growth and prosperity in the West.
And then they threw it away. It is that
generation and that shift which is the
subject of my debut film and Webby
Awards on a re Boomers, which I released
just over a year ago. It follows me on a
road trip around the US and Europe as I
try to uncover the roots of the
intergenerational tensions which sit
beneath so much of our politics today.
It was a massive undertaking and a huge
amount of fun to make. And all of that
was made possible because Boomers is a
Nebula original film. Many of you would
have heard of Nebula by now. Nebula is
the premium streaming service created by
myself and a bunch of other somewhat
nerdy content creator [music] friends.
It allows you to watch all of our usual
videos like this one ad and sponsor free
whilst also giving you access to a ever
expanding catalog of content which
simply isn't available anywhere else.
That includes Boomers, but it also
includes stuff like Tara Mooney's new
series Politits, which explores the
cultural politics of breasts. It's a
whole lot of fun as well as being
really, really interesting. It's also
the kind of project which simply
wouldn't do very well on YouTube. The
whole topic is basically a one-way
ticket to demonetization. One of the big
bonuses of Nebula for both us as
creators and you as viewers is that it
allows us to create great stuff for you
without worrying about whether any of
YouTube's unaccountable content systems
will hide it away. Nebula is also, you
will be happy to know, refreshingly
affordable. If you use my code
go.nebula.tv/don.nicholas,
you can get 50% off an annual
subscription, which brings the total
price down to just £2.50 per month or
whatever your local equivalent is. Or
when you don't want to add another to
your monthly budget, we now also offer
lifetime subscriptions which have proven
really popular. These cost a chunk more
up front, but get you access to Nebula
for as long as both you and the platform
exist. Lifetime subscriptions also help
us to fund future big projects like
Boomers which allow us to grow the
platform and the videos that are
available on there without turning to
shady venture capitalists or something
who might ruin what we think is a pretty
decent product and project. That link
again is go.nebula.tv/tomnicholas.
Thank you so much for watching once
again, and I'll see you over on Nebula.
All that's left for me to do is to say a
massive thank you to the people who
support me at the top tier of my Patreon
over at patreon.com/tomnicholas,
who are Richard, Gary, Dickon Spain,
Bill Mitchell, ZC Reese, Zoe Olden,
Alexander Blank, Niels Hildegard, Sophia
uh Sergio Suarez, Richard Rapoone,
Gabriel Coke, Fiasco Linguini, Agent
Maxwell, Glenn Sugden, Emil Jaraba,
Yilmazson, Paulius Edikas, Sam
Fortunato, Sondre Ylvisaker, Douglas
Urquhart, Ahmed Harajic, and Hasty. If
you want to support them in getting
early access to bits that we're working
on, my updates in terms of what we're
working on and how things are going week
by week, as well as copies of the
scripts to videos and a bunch of other
stuff, then you can find out how to do
so at patreon.com/tomnicholas.
Thank you so much for watching once
again, and I'll see you in the next
video.